<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Concepts on Encompass Docs</title>
    <link>/concepts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Concepts on Encompass Docs</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 12:49:24 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/concepts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Component</title>
      <link>/concepts/component/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 12:51:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/concepts/component/</guid>
      <description>A Component is a collection of related data.
To define a Component, extend the Component class.
import { Component } from &amp;quot;encompass-ecs&amp;quot;; class PositionComponent extends Component { public x: number; public y: number; }  Components are created in context with an Entity.
const entity = World.create_entity(); const position = entity.add_component(PositionComponent); position.x = 3; position.y = -4;  Components cannot exist apart from an Entity and are automagically destroyed when they are removed or their Entity is destroyed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Message</title>
      <link>/concepts/message/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 13:10:43 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/concepts/message/</guid>
      <description>Similar to Components, Messages are collections of data.
Messages are used to transmit data between Engines so they can manipulate the game state accordingly.
To define a message, extend the Message class.
import { Message } from &amp;quot;encompass-ecs&amp;quot;; class MotionMessage extends Message { public x: number; public y: number; }  Messages are temporary and destroyed at the end of the frame.
Ok fine, since you asked, Messages actually live in an object pool so that they aren&amp;rsquo;t garbage-collected at runtime.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Entity</title>
      <link>/concepts/entity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 12:55:22 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/concepts/entity/</guid>
      <description>An Entity is a structure composed of a unique ID and a collection of Components.
Entities do not have any implicit properties or behaviors. They are granted these by their collection of Components.
There is no limit to the amount of Components an Entity may have, and Entities can have any number of Components of a particular type.
Entities are active by default and can be deactivated. They can also be destroyed, permanently removing them and their components from the World.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Engine</title>
      <link>/concepts/engine/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 13:01:28 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/concepts/engine/</guid>
      <description>An Engine is the Encompass notion of an ECS System. Much like the engine on a train, your Engines make the simulation move along.
I never liked the term System. It is typically used to mean structures in game design and I found this confusing when discussing code implementation vs design.
 Engines are responsible for reading the game state, reading messages, emitting messages, and creating or mutating Entities and Components.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Renderer</title>
      <link>/concepts/renderer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 14:16:06 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/concepts/renderer/</guid>
      <description>A Renderer is responsible for reading the game state and telling the game engine what to draw to the screen.
Remember: Encompass isn&amp;rsquo;t a game engine and it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a rendering system. So Renderers aren&amp;rsquo;t actually doing the rendering, they&amp;rsquo;re just telling the game engine what to render.
 There are two kinds of renderers: GeneralRenderers and EntityRenderers.
A GeneralRenderer is a Renderer which reads the game state in order to draw elements to the screen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World Builder</title>
      <link>/concepts/world_builder/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 13:40:25 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/concepts/world_builder/</guid>
      <description>WorldBuilder is used to construct a World from Engines, Renderers, and an initial state of Entities, Components, and Messages.
The WorldBuilder enforces certain rules about Engine structure. It is forbidden to have messages create cycles between Engines, and no Component may be mutated by more than one Engine.
The WorldBuilder uses Engines and their Message read/emit information to determine a valid ordering of the Engines, which is given to the World.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World</title>
      <link>/concepts/world/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 12:51:08 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/concepts/world/</guid>
      <description>World is the pie crust that contains all the delicious Encompass ingredients together.
The World&amp;rsquo;s update function drives the simulation and should be controlled from your engine&amp;rsquo;s update loop.
The World&amp;rsquo;s draw function tells the Renderers to draw the scene.
In LÖVE, the starter project game loop looks like this:
export class Game { private world: World; private canvas: Canvas; ... public update(dt: number) { this.world.update(dt); } public draw() { love.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>